this evening we are proud to present one
of these whistleblowers f CI a agent
John Kerry our COO
he was the first government official to
confirm the use of waterboarding by Bush
administration so I'm really happy here
there are so many things that I'd like
to talk about tonight but I'm going to
try to keep it short because I hope we
can have a conversation afterwards and
some questions and answers and really
get to some of the bottom or to the
bottom of some of these issues but I'd
like to first talk about that was a beta
many of you perhaps most of you know the
story of Abu Zubaydah Abu Zubaydah was
supposed to have been the number three
ranking person in al-qaeda
and when I was stationed in Pakistan as
the chief of counterterrorism operations
for the CIA
liberals are patriots right a Republican
Party and the conservative movement in
this country do not have a monopoly on
patriotism so I was in Pakistan we
received words to capture of Zubaydah he
was somewhere in Pakistan we had to
catch him but Pakistan was the size of
Texas and it is populated by about 270
million people so to say he's somewhere
in Pakistan go catch him and do a
non-starter
anyway we got it March 28th I think it
was 2002 he had been shot while he was
trying to escape a Pakistani policeman
shot him three times with an ak-47 and
he nearly bled to death
about a day and a half later when he
finally came out of a coma we began to
talk I sat by his bedside for 56 hours
and I thought wow this is this is kind
of a unique opportunity maybe an
historic opportunity so I'm gonna make
the most of it and I tried to engage him
in conversation and first he asked me to
kill him he asked me to smother him with
a pillow and once he calmed down we
talked about things like poetry he said
that he would he would never know the
touch of a woman he would never know the
joy of fatherhood he said that he didn't
want to attack the United States on
September 11th he wanted to attack
Israel but he had been overruled am i
funny yep then at that point and I said
listen there were 50,000 people in those
towers that morning what did you think
we were gonna do did you think we
wouldn't come after you did you know did
you not think or assume that we would
try to destroy your group but with that
said I told him I should hate you and I
don't you're pathetic
I feel sorry for you and I said I'm
gonna give you some advice and I hope
you'll take it
I am the nicest guy that you'll need in
this experience my colleagues are not as
nice as I am and you have to cooperate
and he said you seem like a nice man but
you're the enemy and I'll never
cooperate so a day later a CIA jet flew
in to pick him up in the middle of the
night I wished him luck he asked me to
hold his hand as we loaded him onto the
plane and I had no idea where he was
going I recounted a story in my book
where we were waiting for the manifest
to be accepted and an American got off
the plane completely dressed in black
with a black mask
black hat black sweater and a bandolier
and he said John and I said who are you
and he lifted up his mask and he had
been my last boss at headquarters and he
said what are you doing here and I said
oh I'm the I'm the chief of
counterterrorism here I said what are
you doing here he said oh I volunteered
for the flight I'm gonna take your
prisoner onward and he said who is he
and I said jeez I'm sorry but you don't
have a need to know who he is
we haven't even told the Pakistanis who
he was we just called him a big fish and
they referred to him as mr. fish so I
said where are you taking him and he
said I'm sorry but you don't have a need
to know and it wasn't until many months
later that I started hearing these
rumors about secret prisons that the CIA
had I still didn't know anything about
any torture program until I returned
from Pakistan in the early summer of
2002 and a senior officer in the CIA's
Counterterrorism Center approached me
and said listen I wanted to ask you if
you'd be interested in being trained in
enhanced interrogation techniques I said
what does that mean enhanced
interrogation techniques he said very
excitedly we're gonna start getting
rough with these guys and they said what
does that mean rough so he told me these
ten techniques that the CIA was going to
begin using on prisoners I said that
sounds like a torture program I don't
think I want to be involved in that but
I said you know what give me an hour so
I went upstairs to the executive floor
the seventh floor of the CIA
I had a friendly relationship with a
very very senior CIA officer who had
been my boss in the Middle East
Kait earlier and i said he somebody just
approached me and asked me if i wanted
to do this enhanced interrogation
techniques what do you think of this and
he said and he denies that this
conversation ever took place
but he told me first let's call it what
it is it's a torture program second
tortures a slippery slope and you know
how these guys are somebody's going to
go overboard and they're gonna kill a
prisoner and when that happens there's
going to be a congressional
investigation and then there's going to
be a Justice Department investigation
and somebody's going to go to prison do
you want to go to prison I said no I
don't want to go to prison
turn down I'm the only one that went to
prison but I said no I went back down to
the counterterrorism center and I said I
am NOT interested in this it's a torture
program well what the CIA ended up doing
was really criminal in and of itself
before they even laid a hand on Abu
Zubaydah because the FBI was already at
this secret location there was an FBI
agent by the name of Adi su fun
he was a naturalized American of
Egyptian origin if he was a terrific FBI
agent believe me it's like a kink in my
back to compliment the FBI but this guy
was actually really good his job and
what he did once that was a beta began
to recover was he sat across the table
from him he offered him a date or an
apple or an orange or whatever it was
they had and he engaged him in
conversation and over the course of the
next couple of weeks
Abu Zubaydah began to offer highly
actionable intelligence that was used to
disrupt future terrorist attacks and
which probably saved American lives not
by beating him not by freezing him or
putting cockroaches in a box and putting
him in the box with the roaches which we
did because he had a terrible fear of
cockroaches but just by engaging the man
in conversation for whatever reason
George Tenet the director of the CIA
didn't like having the FBI
charge of this operation and so he went
to george w bush and he said I want
primacy in this operation and I want you
to remove the FBI from the country and
George W Bush said ok and so Ali Soufan
was pulled out of the country and was
replaced not only by CIA officers and
CIA contractors but by to contract
psychologists who had been hired
specifically to create a torture program
on August 1st the President signed an
executive order allowing the CIA to
begin torturing elizabeta
this was after the procurement of
specious legal arguments from the
notorious Jay Bybee and John you both of
whom have gone on to great success in
their chosen field of law and so Abu
Zubaydah was tortured now the program
was such that see CIA officers were
supposed to start with the most basic
so-called techniques something like a
smack in the belly right makes a loud
cracking sound humiliates you makes you
angry
you know you can't respond but then they
went up the list very quickly there was
one technique called wobbling for
example that's when you grab the
prisoner by the by the shirt or the
lapels and slam him into a cardboard I'm
sorry a plywood wall now he's supposed
to have either a rolled-up towel around
his neck or one of those sleep pillows
so he doesn't hurt his neck and it's
supposed to be we're all supposed to be
plywood well they forgot to give him the
pillow to protect his neck and the wall
was concrete so sorry about that
I mean that's what the cable said
according to the Senate torture report
it escalated quickly from there
a lot has been made about waterboarding
waterboarding is when a prison
is is tied or shackled to a to a board
or a burning his feet are slightly
elevated some sort of material cloth
burlap is is put either around or in the
mouth and then water is poured on his
face it it gives you the feeling of
drowning and it's it's it's a horrible
thing to see it's a worse thing to go
through but the prisoner will convulse
start to vomit
you're tense your your abdominal muscles
which causes extreme pain and oftentimes
you faint I would posit that that was
not the worst thing that I was a beta in
Doherty there were other techniques but
for whatever reason have not gotten as
much press one was sleep deprivation now
Donald Rumsfeld who is also will work
from though as far as I'm concerned
Donald Rumsfeld made a point of mocking
the fact that that people were
complaining about sleep deprivation as a
torture technique saying I've worked in
my office 48 72 hours at a time and I
have a stand-up desk I don't even have a
chair but we're not talking about 48 or
72 hours
imagine being changed to an eyebolt in
the ceiling where you can't kneel or lay
down and you're kept like that for 14
days now psychologists will tell us that
people begin losing their minds around
day 9 and they begin dying around day 12
if you read the Senate torture report
you'll see that the orders from the CIA
were to not exceed 14 days well if
you're already dead at 12 what's the
point of cutting it off at 14 another
technique was called the cold cellar
where the prisoners changed that same
able to the ceiling and he stripped
naked and the the cell was chilled to 50
degrees and then every hour somebody
comes in and throws a bucket of ice
water on two people were killed by CIA
Oh
using that technique but those officers
were never prosecuted at the very very
least that has to be depraved
indifference or manslaughter if there
was a cable saying do this to him that
wouldn't make it first-degree murder
wouldn't it I mean at the federal level
this would be a federal crime that's a
death penalty case but no one was ever
prosecuted
Abu Zubaydah also underwent something
else that has gotten very little playing
the press when we captured him I noticed
that one of his eyes was a very very
pale blue he was blind in an MRI and it
turned out that it was an old shrapnel
wound from the Afghan war with the
Soviets
well Jason Leopold a reporter at vice
news found through the Freedom of
Information Act that I was debated up
one day was sedated without ever being
told what was happening to him and when
he woke up his eyeball was gone we had
just taken it up we didn't ask him we
didn't ask him if he wanted us to we
just did it that's a crime against
humanity besides the fact that we have
anti torture laws in this country we
always have there's a law called the
federal torture Act it specifically
defines torture and specifically
prohibits it and to see it simply it
defines torture essentially as anything
that makes somebody uncomfortable or
causes them pain and it's not it doesn't
have to be just carried out by someone
on behalf of the government it can be
carried out by someone working on behalf
of someone working on behalf
the government with the bottom line
being don't do it it's illegal so we
have that long books besides that the
United States is a signatory to the UN
Convention Against Torture not only are
we a signatory and one of the one of the
first signatories we wrote the doc on
the United Nations Convention Against
Torture and it contains the same
definition of torture and the same
prohibition of torture or on torture
that the federal torture Act does in
1968 in January the Washington Post ran
a picture on its front page of an
American soldier waterboarding a North
Vietnamese prisoner on the morning that
that photo appeared then Secretary of
State McNamara Robert S McNamara ordered
an investigation the soldier in the
picture was arrested he was tried and
convicted of tortured and imprisoned
well the law didn't change still the
same law
so why was torture illegal in 1968 but
it wasn't illegal
in 2002 or in 2015 when John McCain and
Dianne Feinstein were forced to pass a
bill into law that just reiterated our
ban on torture I would go so far as to
say that CIA aside there is still
torture taking place and it's taking
place right here in the United States
the United Nations has called the u.s.
prison systems use of solitary
confinement confinement as a form of
torture now I'm gonna tell you a story
in this I know firsthand I spent two
years in prison
thanks to Eric Holder and
Obama and I never thought that I would
you know when you're somebody like me
right I'm a middle middle-class white
guy professional master's degree he
finished my PhD coursework never in my
worst nightmares did I ever think I'd
end up in prison with pedophiles and
murderers and drug dealers just the
worst people in the world but you know
prisons don't necessarily have the worst
people in the world in them I mean there
are a lot of there are a lot of people
in prison that I personally felt didn't
belong there
so I want to tell you about one he was
my last cellmate his name was James
James was a mentally ill homeless man
from Pittsburgh and he was living in a
cardboard box under a bridge the Liberty
Street bridge in Pittsburgh and he
violated the terms of his federal parole
just so that he could spend the winter
indoors because it was better to be in
prison through the winter
Pittsburgh winters of ferocious than it
was to be in this cardboard box I walked
into the cell one day and I saw him
sitting on the edge of the bed and I
said hi are you the new guy and he said
yeah I'm James he stood up and shook my
hand and I said hi James I'm John and he
said well nice to meet you John but I
got to tell you something I have severe
mental illness and if I don't take my
medication I'm really crazy like
dangerous crazy and I said Wow I
appreciate you telling me I said we have
a really good seller we all get along
it's all good guys I think you're gonna
fit in fine
and you later I thought never did I
think I'd be friends with him with a
mentally ill homeless man but he was a
really great guy and he had a terrific
sense of humor so he went down to the
medical unit on his first full day to
ask for his medications remember he's
only in on a violation he's only gonna
be there for months and the medication
for paranoid schizophrenia is very
expensive and so in their infinite
wisdom
Eero of prisons and the and the National
Health Service or where they call
themselves with the uniforms Public
Health Service Thank You Public Health
Service officers down there they gave
him Tylenol instead of his mental
schizophrenia paranoid schizophrenia
medication they gave him Tylenol so he
came back up to the south he was very
upset I said James you can't you can't
take this
you know lie down if you're not mentally
ill you have to be medicated don't don't
just take tylenol and then let them get
away with it go back down there and
raise hell and if they won't give you
your medication then fire on them you
know there's this administrative remedy
process and while it doesn't work most
of the time because you're prisoners and
their officers remember who they get who
are people gonna believe the crazy
homeless guy or the uniformed officer
right so I said if they don't give you
your meds
you're gonna file on them at least it'll
go to the warden and you know maybe
maybe the warden would turn out to be a
decent guy he turned out to be an
[__] to tell you the truth but you
know I thought maybe at least you know
you have a chance so James went back
down and they told him that he got what
they were going to give him and he
needed to leave so he filed a complaint
anyway down again the next day and they
told him to get out they weren't gonna
give him any medication so he filed
another complaint and he would do this
every day he did this for like ten days
he would just go down be turned down and
file a complaint well they deemed this
to be harassment against staff and so I
happened to be in the visitors room one
day a friend of mine from high school
came to visit me and it's it's all
windows on one wall and I saw James
being led away in handcuffs which only
meant that I meant I should say only
that they were taking him to solitary
confinement well if your surface on the
Terry for harassing staff you usually go
down there for three or four days until
everybody cools off and then the officer
will go down into solitary and you
apologize
they let you out four or five days came
and went a week two weeks finally they
replace James they put an even crazier
pedophile in his bed so I said boy James
is still in solitary I said to one of
the cellmates of that I don't think
things are good for him down there
because you can guarantee he's not being
medicated in solitary if he wasn't being
medicated in the room and then one day a
Mexican prisoner whom with whom I was
friendly got out of solitary and sent me
a message that he needed to see me so we
arranged to get together outside the
yard where nobody could hear us speaking
and he said you have access to the press
and you've got to tell the public what
happened to James I said what happened
to James and he said he went crazy down
in there he started singing 99 bottles
of beer on the wall which everybody
thought was kind of funny in the
beginning but he sang it for nine hours
without stopping people were screaming
from the other cells
finally he stood up in his bed he took
off his slipper and he hit the sprinkler
in his cell whence then sent the
sprinklers off in every one of the 65
cells and he flooded the cells so of
course just like you see on MSNBC at 11
o'clock at night they send in the SWAT
team with their helmets and their vests
and they tase him and then they beat him
to a bloody pulp after they beat him and
I should add this was his second beating
in prison he was beaten so badly in his
previous prison that he had to be
hospitalized but then the investigation
found that his injuries were
self-inflicted right because we all beat
each other or beat ourselves I should
say up in the face like this right so
his who's told me that after they beat
him they stripped him naked
and they threw them outside into a cage
now you hear you hear a lot about
solitary confinement being 23 hours a
day right you're locked in for 23 hours
and you are but that one hour it's not
like you they just let you go for an
hour each solitary cell has a door a
small dormant which leads into a cage 10
by 8 foot cage and so you're allowed to
just walk in circles in the cage for an
hour and then you come back in that's
your one hour exercise what they call
exercise so they stripped him naked
after beating him and they threw him
outside of the cage now it's January in
the mountains of central Pennsylvania
was ten degrees he Sue's told me that
and first James was apologizing I'm
sorry please let me back in at our two
he began crying and about power three he
fainted
and that's when they brought it in
instead of giving him his medication
they transferred him to a higher
security prison because they said he was
dangerous so of course he's dangerous
because he's crazy and he's crazy
because you won't give him his
medication
now this is not an unusual story this
happens in American prisons every single
day and there's no accountability none
whatsoever
so while we're focused on these secret
prisons that the CIA had been operating
all around the world the same kind of
thing was going on right here at home
under our very noses people asked me a
lot if I think torture still exists
that is US government sponsored torture
if that exists you know with the passage
of the of the McCain fine stein
amendment tortures ban right I want very
much to believe that that torture no
longer exists but everything that the
CIA has told us since
has been a lie everything so why should
we believe them now now they're gonna
start telling the truth
you know I spent 15 years with them
the CIA psychiatrist once told me that
the CIA please don't judge me for this
the CIA seeks to hire people with
sociopathic tendencies not sociopaths
but people with sociopathic tendencies
now sociopaths don't have consciousness
and people with no conscience people who
feel no guilt can easily pass a
polygraph exam but those people are also
hard to manage and hard to control
people with sociopathic tendencies are
comfortable operating in moral or
ethical gray areas but how do you weed
out the sociopaths and we know from
psychological studies that have been
published over the last half a century
that it's the sociopaths that rise to
the top of corporate structures
including the CIA that's why all the
lunatics are the ones in charge because
they can pass the polygraph they can
pass the background investigation and by
god they're going to convince you that
they are patriots
[Music]
there's no ethics training at the CIA
none you either go in there with your
own wall code or you wing it usually
when they speak at colleges and
universities I asked a question and I
think actually I'm gonna ask the same
question and I'm serious about it I'd
like to see show hands let's say that
you are a CIA case officer and you've
recruited a major penetration of a
foreign terrorist al Qaeda Hizballah
Isis whatever you wanted to be this guy
is the real deal and he's he's reporting
to you every month and he's giving you
this actionable intelligence it's going
straight for the president you're
getting promoted and everything is great
right this is every officers dream so he
shows up in a meeting let's say you're
meeting somewhere in the Middle East
maybe in a hotel you have this meeting
and he says listen I've been giving you
the kitchen sink and everything I say is
true and I've saved American lives so
now you're going to do something for me
you're going to go out and you're gonna
get me a prostitute and if you don't get
me a prostitute I'm not gonna work with
you anymore do you get over the
prostitute who says yes yeah sure Jesus
come that you know he's just come back
it's your job to deal with scumbags so
sure you get every prostitute what if he
asks for a child prostitute
yeah absolutely not
absolutely not
not in a million years but there are no
rules and generally you don't really
have to ask anybody for permission you
just do it so if you've got no personal
moral structure or ethical structure
something that you've been taught as a
child or something maybe that you've
even had born into you what do you have
to be not well what's happened is many
of the CIA's leaders at least through
the ill named war on terror didn't have
that ethical background they would be
the kinds of guys who won't get the
child prostitute and not think twice
about it people also ask me a lot how in
the world could you have worked for the
CIA
one of the most murderous and and
criminal organizations in the world I
was born into a into a Greek immigrant
family my grandparents were immigrants
from Greece from the island of Rhodes
and to here my grandfather tell it
Franklin Roosevelt was waiting for him
at Ellis Island to hand him his
citizenship and a job at US Steel we had
until the day he died we had a framed
picture of Franklin Roosevelt on our
television set I still have it I love it
and so my parents raised me to believe
that we were so fortunate to be allowed
into this country and to really be given
the opportunity for success that we
needed to repay it
and you repay it through public service
so I was recruited into the CIA but
before I accepted the position I asked
the boyfriend of a woman I was in
graduate school with about his
experience in the CIA he had been in the
CIA about three years well this is the
1980s so the Church Committee is still
pretty fresh in everybody's mind and I
said to him so what about you know the
assassinations and masonic and Guatemala
and the Dominican Republic I mean did
that stuff just go away yeah yeah we
don't doing that stuff anymore it's
really great you're gonna be happy there
and I said yeah but what about MKULTRA
and all on the other you know love to
see the world and it did went to 65
countries with the CIA
so I joined and I'll tell you the truth
things were actually pretty good through
George HW Bush and Bill Clinton
I remember Bill Clinton ordering
ordering the Director of Operations to
go through its files and to purge
everybody from the the source roles who
had any human rights problems in their
backgrounds because we don't want to be
in the business of associating with
people who had poor human rights records
and I thought wow okay well maybe things
really are changing and and honestly
even in retrospect I think they had been
changing and then September 11th
happened and September 11th just changed
everything again permanently jesselyn
Radack says in the film silenced that
that Brad Thacker mentioned she said I
want my September 10th country back
because you know these things tend to be
a pendulum they're cyclical they go back
and forth but after September 11th they
went like that and never came back down
again you know we've got the the
so-called Patriot Act we have NSA spying
Americans now we have the CIA spying on
Americans they're there they're building
secret prisons and torturing people and
artists of paramilitary fighters and
that's not the CIA I signed on for and
so I decided it was time to leave I'm
probably the only person who when he
says he resigned to spend more time with
his children actually resigned to spend
more time with children but I kept my
mouth shut about everything for years
and then one day in 2007 Brian Ross at
ABC News called me and he said that he
had a source who said that I had
tortured I was a beta I said that was
absolutely untrue I was the only person
who was kind to have as a Vanna
I've never laid a hand on I was a beta
or on any other page I said your source
is either misinformed or he's a liar
well you're welcome to come on the show
and defend yourself he said old
reporters trip that I didn't know
anything about I said I'd think about it
so that week President Bush gave a press
conference in which he liberated the
camera and said we do not torture we do
not torture and I said to my wife who
was also a CIA officer that's a
bald-faced lie he's just looking right
into the eyes of the American people and
he's lying and then a couple of days
after that in response to a reporter's
question he said if there is torture
it's the result of a rogue CIA officer
and I thought I wonder if they're gonna
try to pin this on me tell you the truth
when I walked away from the CIA
I really walked away I didn't pay any
attention these issues anymore I didn't
follow the whole torture to me but in
the back of my mind I sort of recalled
hearing that Human Rights Watch had
issued a report saying the CIA was
torturing prisoners Amnesty
International a year later came out with
the same conclusion and I just in my
mind thought it was it was up there so I
called Brian Ross and I said
on your show the intent was to defend
myself and I also decided that whatever
he asked me I was gonna tell the truth
and so in response to these questions I
said three things that have utterly
changed the course of my life I said the
CIA was torturing its prisoners
I said torture was official US
government policy it was not a road it
was policy and I said the policy was
approved by and signed by the President
himself
thereby calling the president a
bald-faced liar to his face in fact the
president said the next day it's the
only time any president has ever said
anything about me he said I don't know
this man I don't know this man's
motivation I don't know why this man
threw me under the bus I was very proud
to throw turista so the next day the
very next day the CIA filed something
called a crimes report against me with
the Justice Department and they asked
the FBI to begin investigating me that
investigation began in earnest and was
also leaked by the FBI to CNN I read it
in CNN my otherwise had no idea was
under this the investigation lasted a
year from December 2007 to December 2008
after the 2008 elections and the bush
Justice Department decided that I had
not committed a crime and they closed
the investigation a month later
Barack Obama is inaugurated and Eric
Holder becomes Attorney General the CIA
goes to Eric Holder and says that case
against Tyrion cou we want you to reopen
that case I had no idea that this had
happened in the meantime I'm working for
John Kerry as the senior investigator on
the Senate Foreign Relations Committee
and Kerry's Intel
with no idea that I'm under FBI
investigation the investigation lasted
for another four years three years and
other three years and then finally in
2012 just after leaving senator ben
senator Kerry's employ I was charged
with three counts of espionage one count
of violating the Intelligence identities
Protection Act of 1981 I'm only the
second American ever charged with them
and making a false statement and mine
treason is still to this day we're not
clear exactly what the full statement
was supposed to be in any event it was
it was dropped but three counts of
espionage
now the first kind of espionage the CIA
said I had revealed top secret code word
information that was Declassified solely
for the purpose of prosecuting me so
what that information was I'm going to
tell you was that after the September
11th attacks the CIA had a program to
kill or capture members of al-qaeda talk
secret
that's an espionage Church this is a
potential death penalty charge the other
two espionage charges were equally
insane a reporter from the New York
Times called me to say he was writing an
article on a CIA officer who had never
been undercover ever in his life he's on
Facebook
CIA employer CIA works at CIA Lincoln
CIA central intelligence agency never
undergo he resigned anyone to work for a
consultant so this reporter said can you
introduce me to this guy I said I
haven't talked to that guy in years I
don't even know where he is he's
probably in Virginia somewhere and then
I said but you know what I have a
business card I think I still have it I
found it I scanned it by email the two
espionage
Kevin espionage charge for that but
before they could charge me I actually
sent it to a second the journalist one
with whom I was working at the time at
ABC News
that's three espionage charges that they
were all dropped because I hadn't
committed espionage but after my arrest
in the course of discovery we found a
memo that the CIA had written to the
Attorney General's Office and it said
charge it with espionage and the
Attorney General's Office wrote back and
said but he hasn't committed espionage
and the CIA said charge him and make him
defend himself because that's the plan
this is what they do they don't care if
you've committed espionage or not I mean
of the people I believe the numbers up
to nine now under the under the Obama
administration which is triple all
previous presidents combined nine people
charged with espionage none of whom have
ever been accused of passing information
to a foreign government never this is
all for contact with the press so the
point is several fold
number one you scare the hell out of
everybody else who's considering talking
to the press
it's an indirect as a second it's an
indirect threat against journalists went
when the Attorney General himself
identifies a journalist as an unindicted
co-conspirator because he's written an
article that the Attorney General
doesn't like that causes a chilling
effect on freedom of the press and
freedom of speech basic constitutional
rights
third they do something called stacking
they'll charge you not with one crime
they'll charge you with ten or twenty
crimes and they'll make you defend
yourself against those ten or twenty
they're my case five crimes until you're
bankrupt and then they come back and say
all right we'll drop all the charges but
one if you take a plea well what are you
gonna do as Brett said I still have my
attorneys eight hundred and eighty
thousand dollars and that's after giving
them a hundred and fifty thousand which
was everything they had you know we had
to move out of our house my wife my poor
wife was fired from the CIA the day of
my arrest just because she was married
to me we had to go on welfare and when
we went to the welfare office they said
my god you qualify for everything but
they gave us food stamps cash payment
free milk and cheese Medicaid I mean we
qualify for everything they had but
that's the goal the goal is to bankrupt
you so that you'll take complete to
anything to make this go away my
attorneys told me look you've already
spent a million bucks if we go to trial
it's gonna be at least another million
maybe another two million and if we go
to trial you risk forty five years why
I'm 51 years old that's a death penalty
of the high in prison there's no federal
parole you have to do the whole stretch
right Ronald Reagan wanted to get tough
on crime
there's no parole so they're offering
two and a half years it ceases
being I'm innocent they didn't do it and
it becomes an economic decision we
figured she finally got a job about ten
months after she was fired my wife I'm
unemployable but we figured through the
generosity of my brother her father
our friends anonymous supporters we
could make it two years anything more
than two years and were ruined for life
there won't be any come back from that
so we took it and I went to prison for
23 what turned out to be twenty three
months but my story is not as as sad as
Jeffrey sterling story Jeffrey Jeffrey
literally did nothing wrong and there
was no evidence against him but this is
another thing they do and they didn't do
it just to Jeffrey but they did this to
that's known to the government does
something called venue shopping and I'll
give you these two examples Jeffrey
sterling a CIA officer who blew the
whistle to them to the house permanent
Select Committee on Intelligence on a
ill-fated in an ill thought-out
operation against Iran Jeffrey was
living in st. Louis and working remotely
for a company in New York the pace of
st. Louis as the Eastern District of
Missouri New York as the Southern
District of New York he's alleged to
have passed information to Jim risin I
don't think he did but Jim risin lived
in Bethesda Maryland which is the
southern district of Maryland and worked
in Washington DC which is the federal
district of the District of Columbia but
they charged Jeffrey sterling with a
crime actually with nine counts of well
seven counts of espionage and two counts
of theft of government property which
was the information right he walked out
of the building with the
in his head so that staff fell me but
they charged him in the Eastern District
of Virginia so why because the Eastern
District of Virginia is known as the
espionage Court and nobody ever wins
there ever there's one judge in
particular judge Leonie bring him up
ironically a Clinton appointee who
deserves every national security case
for herself and no one has ever won
well Jeffrey said from the beginning I
didn't do anything wrong
all the feds had on Jeffrey was that he
had made 52 phone calls
over the course of five years to jim
risin at the new york times well Jim
risin was covering Jeffrey's civil suit
against the CIA the CIA passed him over
for promotions solely because he was
black
in fact his boss had told him we can't
send you overseas because you'll stick
out and Jeffrey said when did you
realize I was black so he resigned he
was passed over for promotion because he
wasn't overseas but he couldn't go
overseas because he couldn't fit in so
he resigned and he filed a civil suit
against the agency the agency argued
that it could not defend itself because
to do so would cause them to reveal
national security secrets and so judge
Lee any brinkema
dismissed the case with prejudice on
national security grounds so all the
government had was that Jeffrey had
spoken 52 times over the course of five
years to jim ricin in the meantime in
2006 jim rising writes a book called
bush it more in which he talks about
this botched operation the CIA was
incensed that this information leaked
out and they said who could have done it
that Jeffrey sterling I did it he's
angry with us because we we passed him
over
promotion we got a suit thrown out it
had to be him charge him with espionage
and he did seven counts of espionage and
then these two counts of theft now there
is no proof there were no emails there
were no telephone recordings there were
no clandestine meetings nothing the
government offered no evidence
whatsoever they could have been talking
about the weather I mean ten times over
five years I mean 50 times over five
years ten times a year that's less than
once a month but they convicted him
because in the Eastern District of
Virginia as the old saying goes the jury
they were convicted bologna sandwich you
could appeal yes Jeffrey can appeal and
he is appealing right now you can only
appeal that's a great question
you can only appeal if you have gone to
trial and lost a trial
I took a plea and whenever you take a
plea it comes with a proviso that you
cannot appeal and you cannot file a
Freedom of Information Act request on
yourself to see if there was any FBI
wrongdoing and of course the
investigation so Jeffrey's going to
appeal his wife Holly on Tuesday is
presenting a petition to the White House
with 110,000 signatures asking the
President to pardon him this president's
not getting part of him just like this
president's not going to pardon me so
it's up to all of us to express our
support I can't because I'm a felon and
if I write to Jeffery I'll go back to
prison because that would be consorting
with known felons but you can certainly
express your support I've used up my
time thank you very much for being here
this is a really important group and a
really important cause we have to stick
together and do the best we can it's an
uphill battle
because we have fascists running our
country and I mean fascists of both
parties president abolish the CIA
I met with Oliver Stone day before
yesterday for two and a half hours and
he said that President Kennedy said he
wanted to abolish the CIA and then ended
up with two bullets in his head so
technically sure the president can
abolish the CIA but in the near future
Senator Daniel Patrick Moynihan tried to
raise this in Congress in 1976 1977 he
was a senator from New York and he
argued quite persuasively even in those
times that the CIA a clandestine
intelligence collection could very
easily be done by the Pentagon's
defense human services commander and
that the CIA's analytic arm the director
of intelligence could very easily be
folded into the State Department's
Bureau of intelligence and research
science and technology can be split
between the Pentagon and NASA and then
administration you wouldn't eat any more
because there wouldn't be a CIA and he
wrote a book about this that was quite
well received so I think the answer is
sure we can abolish the CIA I don't
think we will but you could tell me have
another one here
and I'm really happy that you're here
and talking about this thank you and I
won't get through this without crying
but my son my son was a combat medic in
the army
and his job when he got to Iraq in I'm
sorry and September of 2003 was to keep
prisoners alive so they could be
tortured wrong and he was writing
letters home so I knew this was going on
and I spoke about it
every chance I could get and everybody
told me I was absolutely crazy I was out
of my mind that's we don't do that
the president said we don't do that
peace Group said we're not really sure
we can't really talk about it I said I
know because I have the letters and he
can't make this stuff up so he's a 100%
disabled now and from not just the
post-traumatic stress of being in Ramadi
and having that job but from the moral
injury and most people don't have an any
idea what moral injury is moral injury
cannot be healed moral injury there's no
skills to learn to get through it
like there is with post-traumatic stress
and I won't call it a disorder
because it's not a disorder so he's one
of the guys who could be one of the 22 a
day who commits suicide so right now
he's doing where they cut up military
uniforms and make them into paper and
it's called combat paper project he also
revealed did a short documentary with
him in it his name is Eli right the
documentary is called behind the mask
it's on YouTube I encourage you all to
look it up to really get a little vision
and when you look at it and you see the
mask that's him and the mask that's his
friend who also participated in that and
took his own life and you see the mask
at the innocent man
I know that guy's name because Rose
Hulman told me we can't there's no
yellow ribbons there's no songs there's
no Flags large enough to cover what
we've done and continue to do in the
world and I can't tell you how
appreciative I am it's hard for me to be
here because that will never heal and
our family it's also a wood that will
never heal in the families of the people
that we touch over there
wherever over there is so I really
appreciate it thank you your sacrifice I
know that it's no consolation to you but
we know from the Senate torture report
that what your son said was true it was
all true
[Applause]
[Music]